Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is 34, ל"ד, Lamed
Dalet, we actually are already halfway done 34, these דפים dapim are
very short because there are long תוספותים, Tosafotim, so we're actually going
to cover today both 34 and most of 35. So we pick
up with the very last line on ל"ד עמוד א' Lamed Dalet
Amud Aleph which is, or the two last lines אלא אידמיא. ela
idamya. And the case was a case about somebody who had a
witness that he had eaten three years of חזקה chazaka
and that wasn't good because he had only had one witness, he
needed two witnesses, and he was going to have to therefore not
be able to keep the land, and the question was would that
one witness be a witness against him that would make him have
to pay for the three years of the fruit, because if there
is no testimony that he had eaten the fruit and only he
had admitted that he had eaten the fruit and he said he
didn't eat because he had bought the land, then it would be
פה שאסר פה שהתיר, peh she'asar peh shehitir, that wouldn't be enough
to be a concession to make him have to pay. So the
only thing that's making him pay is the one witness that says
that he ate the fruit himself, the witness that says he ate
the fruit. But that witness is actually half of the evidence that
will let him keep the land and he's claiming that he's got
another witness. So it's not clear whether that could make him pay,
and actually the way the גמרא Gemara was tried to use a
comparison to a story of נסקא דרבי אבא Naska de-Rabbi Abba which
we'll get back to in a second, but it said it wasn't
similar because in the נסקא דרבי אבא Naska de-Rabbi Abba case the
one witness was operating against him and had there been two witnesses
he would have been hurt, and in this case when the one
witness says he ate three years if there's a second witness he'll
be helped. So the weight of the one witness by himself who
says he ate three years might not actually be
considered, that's still in his
supportive evidence category which he just doesn't have a second witness for
yet and therefore it could be that that cannot be used to
make him have to pay, that seems to be although the גמרא
Gemara doesn't say explicitly seems to be how the גמרא Gemara was
concluding. But now we have one sentence to say what would be
similar to the case of the נסקא דרבי אבא Naska de-Rabbi Abba
if not this case. The נסקא דרבי אבא Naska de-Rabbi Abba was
somebody
said grabbed something like an ingot of silver that belonged to somebody
else and he said yes I took it but I took something
that was my own and there was one witness who said that
he took it. Now in that case if there were two witnesses
that said that he took it he would be a גזלן gazlan
and he'd have to pay. If there were no witnesses he would
be believed because he could have said I always had
it, believe me that I took my own thing מיגו migo I
could have said that I always had it. So what do you
do in one witness? So רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said well that
witness obligates him to take a שבועה shvu'ah that he did not
steal it because that witness is a damning witness as opposed to
our case of the three years. That witness is a damning witness.
If there would have been two witnesses that he took it he
would have been a גזלן, gazlan, so one witness that he took
it makes him a presumptive גזלן. gazlan. He's חייב chayav to contradict
the witness and take an oath that he did not take it.
Since he can't do that because he says he did take it,
he just took his own thing, he's obligated in a שבועה, shvu'ah,
he can't make a שבועה shvu'ah and he has to pay. So
what would be an analogous case to that by land for us?
Not a witness that says three years, that's not a damning witness
because with one more it actually is a supporting witness. So what
would be a case of a damning witness? So that's the last
line here on ל"ד עמוד א' Lamed Dalet Amud Aleph and the
גמרא Gemara says אלא אידמיא הא דרבי אבא ela idamya ha de-Rabbi
Abba if you want to make a case with land similar to
the case of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba so what would that case
be? לחד סהדא le-chad sahada one witness like we've been talking about
ולתרתי שני ולפירי u-le-tartei shani u-le-piri not three years which is half
of a supporting pair of witnesses but two years and regarding the
question of fruit. So basically just what we've been talking about except
two years. So I say that I have a חזקה, chazaka, I'm
looking for witnesses that I've been on it for three years, I
can't find any witnesses that I've been on it for three years,
I have a witness, there is a witness that says I've been
on it for two years. In that case even though you could
say that's also a little bit of a support of me because
I can now find another witness that says I was the third
year and then another witness that would maybe testify to all three
so I'd fill it all the holes, but right now all I
have is the one witness that says two years. And if there
were two witnesses that said I ate two years that would be
damning witnesses. They would not support my case. They would say two
years, that does not give me a חזקה chazaka and that's evidence
that I ate the fruit and that would obligate me to pay
for the fruit. So if I had two witnesses I'd have to
pay for the fruit. If there were no witnesses I wouldn't have
to pay for anything, there's no evidence I ate the fruit, I'm
saying I did but I'm also saying it's my land. Okay now
we have a middle case just like רבי אבא Rabbi Abba that
there's one witness that says I ate two, I ate two years.
of a fruit, but again a damning witness because with another one
I would be liable. So because that's in the category of a
damning witness I would have to now take an oath to contradict
and to say I did not eat two years of fruit. But
I can't take that oath because I said I did eat the
years of fruit, I just said I owned it. So therefore that's
just like רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, yes I took something, I took
it but it was mine, I can't take an oath to swear
against the witness that says that and say I didn't take it
because I'm admitting that I did take it, I'm obligated in a
שבועה, shvua, I can't make a שבועה, shvua, I have to pay.
Okay so that would be an exact parallel to the רבי אבא,
Rabbi Abba, to the נוסחא nas-ha of רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. We'll
now continue with the top of למד דלת עמוד בית. Lamed Daled
Amud Bet. ההוא ארבא, Hahu arba, there was a boat. דהוו מינצו
עליה בי תרי, d'havu mintzu alei be krei, the two people were
fighting about.
And this is this סוגיא sugya right now is very very related
to the opening סוגיא sugya בבא מציעא Bava Metzia of two people
holding onto a טלית tallit and there the principle is you split
it, but that's a place where two people it's physically in their
possession and therefore the most logical thing is each one is considered
to be possessing all of it or possessing half of it or
in control of all or half, so you cut it in half
and you say יחלוקו. yachloku. And the גמרא Gemara there compares it
to other cases where sometimes you say יחלוקו yachloku and sometimes you
have other resolutions. Here we're not dealing with something that is מטלטלין
metaltelin and chattel that you can be physically in possession of, we're
dealing with things like plots of lands and boats which you can
make claims about but not be physically in possession of. So therefore
the resolutions are going to be different. Let's take a look. ההוא
ארבא, Hahu arba, so there was a boat. דהוו מינצו עליה בי
תרי, d'havu mintzu alei be krei, two people were fighting about. האי
אמר דידי הוא והאי אמר דידי הוא, Hai amar didi hu v'hai
amar didi hu, this one says it's mine, that one says it's
mine. אתא חד מינייהו לבי דינא ואמר תפסוה עד דמייתינא סהדי דדידי
הוא. Ata chad minayhu l'vei dina v'amar tifsuha ad d'maitina sahadei d'didi
hu.
So before we get to the question of what are we going
to do if there's no currently other evidence being brought, what resolution
are we going to have, we're actually first going to address the
question of a holding pattern. One of them says look, can you
please take possession of this boat so that because it's going to
take me some time to collect my evidence? And while I'm collecting
my evidence I don't want this guy to go ahead and steal
it out from under me and sell it, and it's a very,
you know, dear, like it'll be harder for me because once he
sells it he'll put his money in some Swiss bank account or
it has a lot of sentimental value. I'm just asking you to
take possession of this to hold on to it so to give
me time to bring the evidence, to bring the proof that I
need to prove before he can go ahead and do something with
this boat. So will we take possession in as like in a
holding pattern? That's the question. תפסינן או לא תפסינן, Tafsinan o lo
tafsinan, do we take possession of it or not? Do we hold
on to it? רב הונא אמר תפסינן, Rav Huna amar tafsinan, we
do hold on to it, we're willing to play that job of
a referee till things, you know, be involved in a not a
yet a judicial capacity, but in a way to try to hopefully
ensure long term that justice is done. רב יהודה אמר לא תפסינן,
Rav Yehuda amar lo tafsinan,
we don't. Now why not? Well we'll see in a minute because
of the question of what options do we have at the end
if once we choose to get involved. אזל ולא אשכח סהדי, Azal
v'lo ashkhach sahadei, now we went ahead and we did grab it.
However you rule, you rule that we are supposed to grab it,
you rule we shouldn't have taken a hold of it, but we
went ahead and we did it anyway. But למעשה l'maaseh we took
hold of it, this boat. And then the guy who said he
has witnesses to bring can't find the witnesses. So now we're back
to a place that everybody's making claims and nobody has any evidence.
So that puts us in an awkward position, we're holding on to
a boat. What are we supposed to do now? So אמר להו
אפקוה וכל דאלים גבר. amar lehu afkuha v'chol d'alim gvar.
So now he says okay, I can't find my witnesses, so one
of them or whoever one says, now let's get to the ruling
which we haven't said yet but we're going to say, that if
this one claims the boat is mine and this claims the boat
is mine and nobody has any witnesses and nobody's in possession, if
we were in physical possession like a טלית tallit we would say
יחלוקו. yachloku. But nobody has possession, we basically just say go do
what you want, we can't get involved, we have no evidence, we
have nothing to base our decision on. כל דאלים גבר, Chol d'alim
gvar, whoever is stronger wins. Now there's a whole debate in the
ראשונים Rishonim what that means. Does it literally mean physical strength? Does
it mean the first person to grab it? Does it mean that
we're not going to get involved until somebody brings proof, whoever has
stronger proof? But certainly the way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it and
it fits sort of nicely with this גמרא Gemara is look, if
there's no evidence then and no just random claims and no physical
possession, we can't play any role here, we're just leaving it to
you guys to figure out among yourselves. So now that we're in
possession of this boat because we were asked to hold on to
it till evidence could be brought and now it's clear no evidence
is being brought, are we going to now release it and let
them fight it out? Okay sort of like the question before about
זילותא דבי דינא, ziluta d'vei dina, will we reverse ourselves to a
unresolved situation? Or do we feel that we... Once we have taken
possession of it, now we have a responsibility, we can't say, you
know, we're washing our hands. Now we have a responsibility, and we
have to keep on holding on to it until we can figure
out who it belongs to. And if we can never figure out
who it belongs to, we're going to hold on to it, you
know, ad infinitum. Once you get involved, you know, you become responsible.
So what's the story? רב הונא אמר תפסינן, Rav Huna amar tafsinan,
רב יהודה אמר לא תפסינן. Rav Yehuda amar lo tafsinan. Oh, sorry,
I skipped the right... מפקינן ולא מפקינן. mafkinan u-lo mafkinan.
So now will we, you know, take it out of our possession
once there's no evidence. רב יהודה אמר לא מפקינן, Rav Yehuda amar
lo mafkinan, you don't take it out of possession. Once you hold
on to it, then you're responsible. So even if there's no evidence
now, you have to keep on holding on to it. רב פפא
אמר מפקינן. Rav Pappa amar mafkinan. רב פפא Rav Pappa says, no,
once there's no evidence, we are allowed to step away. So what
רשבם Rashbam says is he says, you know, how you're going to
פסקן pasken at the end affects how you're פסקן paskening at the
beginning. And it actually works—רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, it's clear, because since
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is going to say since if you take
hold of it you cannot let go of it, once you take
hold of it you're responsible, that's why it's the same רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda that says I'm not going to—I will not listen to
them to take hold of it because one guy is claiming he
needs to bring more evidence. You're asking me please take hold of
it I need to bring more evidence, I'm going to say, listen
buddy, I refuse. Taking hold of it makes me responsible for adjudicating
and you might not find that evidence, and then we're going to
be stuck holding on and responsible for this boat. So that's why
because I won't be able to release it in the end, says
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, because once I take it I'm responsible, I
don't want to take it in the beginning. Whereas if you take
a position like רב פפא, Rav Pappa, that you even once you
took it you can go ahead and let go of it, then
you'd be much more prepared to agree to take hold of it
from the outset. Okay. רב פפא אמר מפקינן. Rav Pappa amar mafkinan.
והלכתא ובהלכה לא תפסינן Ve-hilchesa u-va-halacha lo tafsinan
that you do not take hold of it because you don't want
to be responsible. If the guy says give me time, I'm sorry,
there's no evidence here, we're not getting involved. Because if we got
involved here to do a holding pattern, we might get stuck holding
the bag, we don't want to be responsible. והיכא דתפס לא מפקינן
Ve-heicha de-tafas lo mafkinan and exactly for that reason if you actually
did go ahead and take hold of it, you did not follow
the rules and you did take hold of it, then you're stuck
with it. Once you take hold, you have to be responsible. Okay,
so that's the question of, but already assuming that our general orientation
here is let's not get involved, are we willing to get involved
in a not-yet-adjudicating way but in a holding pattern? And the answer
is: don't get involved if you can't get yourself out of it
afterwards. Okay. זה אומר של אבותי וזה אומר של אבותי. Zeh omer
shelo avosai ve-zeh omer shelo avosai. Now we're going to actually
get
to the case on which this is based on. What is the
ruling when nobody can bring evidence? This one says that this, you
know, plot of land or this boat or whatever it is, something
that they're not in physical possession of, belongs to my fathers. And
this one says no, belongs to my fathers. And nobody has any
proof. אמר רב נחמן כל דאלים גבר, Amar Rav Nachman kol d'alim
gavar, whoever is stronger
will be victorious. Okay, which again, the way the רשבם Rashbam reads
it, means just like, you guys have no evidence, random claims, we
are not getting involved. Okay, it's up to you guys to figure
it out. Others want to say more it means, you know, we
don't want to just completely throw up our hands, whoever brings more
proof, maybe we'll make it based on more of a, you know,
circumstantial evidence, but we're going to read it like the רשבם. Rashbam.
ומאי שנא משני שטרות היוצאין ביום אחד? U-mai shena mi-shnei shtaros ha-yotzin
be-yom echad?
Now, how is this different than if you have two שטרות shtaros
that come on the same day? One שטר shtar says, ראובן Reuven
says, writes a שטר shtar that says I am gifting my beloved
yellow Ferrari to שמעון, Shimon, and then a שטר shtar dated on
the exact same day says I'm gifting my beloved yellow Ferrari to
לוי. Levi. All right, and there's absolute—and so it can't be to
both of them. What do you do in that case? All right,
and now, and you might be thinking well maybe there's evidence which
one was written first and that's the one that's binding, but another
גמרא Gemara addresses this and says that unless you're in a place,
a locale, where you write the hour in the document itself, which
was not the standard at all, then they take effect at the
end of the day, and if he actually did write both of
them, they should both have taken effect at the exact same time
at the end of the day. So—but it can't both take effect.
So what do you do in that case? So top of ל"ה
ע"א, lamed-heh amud aleph, דרב אמר יחלוקו, De-Rav amar yachloku, רב Rav
says you split it. ושמואל אמר שודא דדייני. U-Shmuel amar shuda d'dayni.
No, the judges make an assessment based on who they think ראובן
Reuven really—their read of the circumstances and their best guess at what
ראובן Reuven's intention was, even though there's no absolute way to prove
it. Right? So why there do we sort of say either split
it or best guess, whereas here we say, you guys, we're not
touching
it? התם ליכא למיקם עלה דמילתא הכא איכא למיקם עלה דמילתא. hasam
leika le-mikam ala de-milsa hacha ika le-mikam ala de-milsa. Okay, because in
the case of the שטר shtar there's no way to prove it.
You have all the evidence you're ever going to have. Two שטרות
shtaros written on the same day for the same object to different
people. Even if you knew which one that ראובן Reuven liked more
or was thinking, that doesn't affect the halachic reality. The halachic reality
is what effects the transfer of property was the שטר, shtar, the
שטרות shtaros are identical and they're written to two different people, so
there's no more evidence to
bring. So we're going to get involved and we'll do the best
we can, the best we can is either split it or try
to assess the דעת. da'as. Okay, but at least there we have
all the evidence we can and we'll try to do the best
we can with that evidence. In this
case, presumably, hopefully, eventually you can find some documentation who owned the
land, some witnesses, some something, so we're not going to make a
judgment when right now there's no evidence and it's possible that further
evidence can be brought. Makes a lot of
sense. ומאי שנא מהא דתנן, Umai shena meha d'tenan, so how's it
different from the following case? המחליף פרה בחמור וילדה Hamachalif parah bachamor
v'yaldah וכן המוכר שפחתו וילדה. v'chein hamocher shifchaso v'yaldah. Okay, so somebody
swaps a cow with a donkey and because it's
חליפין, chalipin, you don't have to have the other object in sight
when it's happening. So ראובן Reuven takes שמעון's Shimon donkey and then
שמעון Shimon owns ראובן's Reuven cow wherever the cow might be. And
then it turns out when they go to collect the cow, they
see that the cow has given birth to a calf. And the
question is did it give birth before the swap took place or
after? Whose calf is it? ראובן's Reuven calf or שמעון's Shimon calf?
Or similarly if somebody sells their maidservant and this you can sell
with money but also the maidservant, female slave doesn't have to be
present. And then when you go to pick up the slave, she
has given birth. Did it give birth before the sale or after
the sale? זה אומר עד שלא מכרתי ילדה, Zeh omer ad shelo
macharti yaldah, before I sold it, my slave or cow gave birth,
so it's my baby cow or my baby slave. וזה אומר משלקחתי
ילדה, Vezeh omer mishekachti yaldah, no it happened after I purchased it.
יחלוקו, Yachloku, we say you split it. So there also presumably
there's no more evidence to be had. Well, maybe that would be
one reason, maybe there would be more evidence to be had and
maybe that's why it's similar to our case. Why should we say
split it? Maybe somebody will come and somebody will have witnessed it
and we'll be able to get some more evidence. So that seems
like a case where maybe there could be more evidence, but we
say split it. Why is that different than our case? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, התם Hasam להאי l'hai top of ל"ה עמוד
ב Lamed Hey Amud Beis אית ליה דררא דממונא is lei drara
d'mamona ולהאי אית ליה דררא דממונא. u'lehai is lei drara d'mamona. In
that case, each one has some type of monetary basis or monetary
connection. There's a question exactly how to translate the word דררא, drara,
but let's say it means connection. So each one has a claim,
has it's not just
סתם, stam, they're just saying stuff out of thin air. Oh, this
is mine. Any Joe off the street could say this is mine,
this is mine, this is mine. You're a random person. Why should
we even get involved in your case, in the case about the
land? You're just making a random claim. Here each one has a
clear stake. We know exactly what happened. We know this one owned
the cow at this point and at the later point that one
owned the cow and the question was when the cow gave birth.
So each one has clear standing in the case and therefore that
forces us as a בית דין Beis Din to come to terms
with us because we know they have a right and they have
a claim why they should say that the calf was this one's
or the calf was that one's. So when they have standing and
a claim, we have to deal with it and even though maybe
more evidence will come to light later, they're demanding a resolution now,
so we'll say יחלוקו. yachloku. In the case about the land or
the boat, these could be just total yahoos. They have absolutely no
standing, so we're going to say you guys just fight it out,
don't bother us. Okay. הכא אי דמר לא דמר ואי דמר לא
דמר Hacha ei d'mar lo d'mar v'ei d'mar lo d'mar
and in this case if it's this one's, it's not that one's,
if it's this one's, it's not that one's. And that sounds a
little bit differently than my point about these they're just total
yahoos, but
some want to read into that that it means that in the
case of the calf, in theory it could be both of theirs
because maybe it gave birth at exactly that split second, whereas in
this case by the land, in theory it can't be both of
theirs, which isn't clear why that's true. Maybe it was owned equally
by their parents. So this line, if it's this one's, it's not
that one's, if it's that one's, it's not this one's, it's better
to be read along this line of whether they clearly have a
stake. Meaning it doesn't mean the land is definitely one or the
others. It means in the case of the calf or of the
cow, we know at one point the calf the cow belonged to
one person, at the next time the cow belonged to the other
person. Each one clearly has a stake in the money to some
degree, in the property, and the question is what about the calf?
In this case, according to this one's claim, the other one has
nothing is complete is a complete
joker, he has he's just making stuff up. And according to the
other one's claim, that one's a complete joker. So neither of them
have any basis to their claims and therefore no proof of any
standing and therefore we say כל דאלים גבר. kol d'alim gvar. כל
דאלים גבר. Kol d'alim gevar. Okay. אמרי נהרדעא Amri Naharda says נהרדעא.
Nehardea. אם בא אחד מן השוק והחזיק בה אין מוציאין אותה מידו.
Im ba echad min hashuk vehichzik bah ein motzi'in otah miyado. If
what happens if so these two Yahoos making their claim,
ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, that the boat is theirs, and we
say כל דאלים גבר, Kol d'alim gevar, so if a third guy
comes and he's the one that takes possession, then נהרדעא Nahardai says,
he can hold onto it, he's just a third Yahoo. Just because
they were the first two Yahoos that came to בית דין, Beis
Din, they all of a sudden have—it's between the two of them
and nobody else? That really shows the point that like why we're
not getting involved, because who the heck is any particular person to
have a claim more than anybody else. דתני רבי חייא Detani Rabbi
Hiyya because רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya teaches גזלן של רבים לאו שמיה
גזלן. Gazlan shel rabim lav shmei gazlan. Somebody who's a גזלן gazlan
of the masses is not a גזלן. gazlan. What does that mean?
It means here, it's not really of the רבים, rabim, you're stealing
something that really is ownerless, you know, it's of the רבים rabim
in the sense not that it's public goods, but it's nobody's goods.
It's everybody's goods. Nobody has any claim to it. So you're not
any more of a גזלן gazlan than these two people are because
nobody has any clear claim to it. Makes a lot of sense.
רב אשי אומר לעולם שמיה גזלן. Rav Ashi omer le'olam shmei gazlan.
Now רב אשי Rav Ashi says no actually these are the two
people that made the claim, this third person doesn't have a stake.
Now why not? Maybe according to רב אשי Rav Ashi it's not
that the third person says no it was my father's and he's
just jumping in on the fun, because if you ask me, why
should he be any less able to make a claim more than
the first ראובן Reuven and שמעון? Shimon? But maybe for רב אשי
Rav Ashi this guy's just taking it without any claim, saying, you
know, you say it's yours, you say it's yours, neither of you
can prove it, I'm not claiming it's my father's but we have
no idea who it is, I'm just going to take it myself.
That maybe makes a little bit more sense about what the case
is we're talking about because it would seem to me that a
third guy can equally claim it's my father's and join in on
the fun. But if he's just סתם stam taking it, so then
the first claim is okay, סתם stam taking it, but you don't
know who—but we have no idea who owned it, so you can
hold onto it because we have no clear person who can say
you took it from them. רב אשי Rav Ashi says no. You're
not making a claim that it's yours, so at least you have
to put it back where it was and let these two guys
or anybody else who makes a claim that it's theirs come and
argue it out. ומאי לאו שמיה גזלן, U'mai lav shmei gazlan, so
what's the statement of a גזלן gazlan of the רבים rabim is
not a גזלן? gazlan? That doesn't mean our case, a גזלן gazlan
of some object that doesn't have any clear owner, you know, nobody
can clearly prove their ownership. No. It literally means a גזלן gazlan
of the רבים. rabim. Somebody who stole something like a public good,
you know, stole water from a well or was robbing people because
they were overcharging everybody in their store. In that case, he's not
a גזלן gazlan in the sense of שלא ניתן להשבון. shelo nitan
lehishavon. He cannot do, you know, restitution because you cannot ultimately pay
back all the people that you stole from. Okay, we will end
here.